<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="jahlborn@users.sf.net">James Ahlborn</author>
    <title>Upgrading from Jackcess 2.x to 3.x</title>
  </properties>
  <body>

    <section name="Jackcess 3.5">
      <subsection name="So what changed, now?">
        <p>
          Jackcess 3.5 is binary compatible with previous 3.x versions.
          However, a few default settings have changed which will change the
          behavior of Jackcess out of the box.  The old behavior is still
          available, but you must now configure it explicitly.
          <ul>
            <li><b>DateTypeType default has been changed to
            LOCAL_DATE_TIME.</b></li>
            <ul>
              <li>The Jackcess API was originally built using the Date type
              for representing date/time values.  However, Access databases
              are inherently "local" time (they contain no timezone info).
              The LocalDateTime type in jdk8+ is a more accurate value for
              relaying Access date/time values.  As of the 3.0 release, the
              Jackcess API supported using <i>either</i> date/time type,
              depending on the configured DateTimeType for the Database.
              However, in order to maintain backwards compatibility, the
              default was kept as DATE.  As of the 3.5 release, the default is
              now LOCAL_DATE_TIME.  The legacy behavior is still available,
              and can be enabled by configuring the DateTimeType appropriately
              (either per Database or via system property).</li>
            </ul>
            <li><b>Expression evaluation is enabled by default.</b></li>
            <ul>
              <li>Optional expression evaluation was added back in the 2.2
              release, but left disabled as the implementation matured.  The
              support is mature enough now to enable this behavior by default.
              Expression evaluation can still be disabled by configuring the
              Database appropriately (either per Database or via system
              property).</li>
            </ul>
          </ul>
        </p>

        <h4>Working with Jackcess Encrypt</h4>
        <p>
          If you are using the <a href="https://jackcessencrypt.sourceforge.io/">Jackcess Encrypt</a> project, then you will need to
          use a version compatible with the relevant Jackess API.
          The version 3.5 release maintains compatibility with the Jackcess
          Encrypt 3.x releases.
        </p>

      </subsection>
    </section>

  </body>

</document>
