<?xml version="1.0"?>

<document>
  <properties>
    <author email="jahlborn@users.sf.net">James Ahlborn</author>
    <title>Upgrading from Jackcess 2.x to 3.x</title>
  </properties>
  <body>
    
    <section name="Jackcess 3.0">
      <subsection name="So what changed?">
        <p>
          Unlike the change from 1.x to 2.x, the change from 2.x to 3.x is
          relatively non-impactful.  The major change was that 3.x requires
          Java 8+.  Other than that, the Jackcess API should be binary
          compatible with existing code.  Some additional notes:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li><b>Dependencies have been updated.</b></li>
          <ul>
            <li>Commons-lang has been replaced with Commons-lang3.  This is
            used internally so it should not really affect code using the
            Jackcess API.</li>
            <li>Log4j is no longer referenced at all.  The included logging
            file is now configured for the java.util logging framework.  Of
            course any bridge compatible with Commons-logging may still be
            utilized.</li>
            <li>The optional Apache POI dependency has been updated to
                4.0 (if utilized for advanced OLE support).</li>
          </ul>
          <li><b>LocalDateTime is now the preferred date/time type.</b></li>
          <ul>
            <li>There are now parallel LocalDateTime based methods for all
            Date based methods.  That said, use of these two collections of
            methods is mutally exclusive.  By default, the backwards
            compatible Date based methods are enabled.  The LocalDateTime
            based methods can be enabled by setting the appropriate
            <a href="apidocs/com/healthmarketscience/jackcess/DateTimeType.html">DateTimeType</a> on the Database.</li>
          </ul>
          <li><b>Path is now supported.</b></li>
          <ul>
            <li>There are now parallel Path based methods for all File based
                methods.</li>
          </ul>
        </ul>

        <h4>Working with Jackcess Encrypt</h4>
        <p>
          If you are using the <a href="https://jackcessencrypt.sourceforge.io/">Jackcess Encrypt</a> project, then you will need to
          use a version compatible with the relevant Jackess API.
          Fortunately, the major versions match, so it's pretty simple:
        </p>
        <ul>
          <li>Jackcess 3.x -&gt; Jackcess Encrypt 3.y</li>
          <li>Jackcess 2.x -&gt; Jackcess Encrypt 2.y</li>
          <li>Jackcess 1.x -&gt; Jackcess Encrypt 1.y</li>
        </ul>
      </subsection>

      <subsection name="What does this mean for 2.x?">
        <p>
          Moving forward, all new feature development will be in Jackcess 3.x.
          Some bugfixes may be backported to a 2.x branch on a case by case
          basis.  However, no new feature development will be done on the 2.x
          branch.
        </p>
      </subsection>

    </section>
  </body>
</document>
